<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="authentication">
  <title>Cockpit Authentication</title>

    <para>While cockpit allows you to monitor and administer several servers at the
      same time, there is always a primary server your browser connects to
      that runs the Cockpit web service (cockpit-ws) through which connections to
      additional servers are established.
      See <ulink url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cockpit-project/cockpit/main/doc/cockpit-transport.png">this diagram</ulink> for how it works.</para>

      <para>Normally, a session is established on the primary server,
      and you use the Shell UI of that session to connect to secondary
      servers.</para>

      <para>However, it is also possible to instruct the
      <filename>cockpit-ws</filename> process on the primary server to
      directly connect to a secondary server, without opening a
      session on the primary server at all. This is done on the main
      login page of Cockpit, by filling out the "Connect to"
      field.</para>

  <section id="initial-auth">
    <title>Directly logging into the primary server</title>

    <para>The most common way to use Cockpit is to just log directly
    into the server that you want to access. This can be done if you
    have direct network access to port 9090 on that server.</para>

    <para>By default the cockpit web service is installed on the base system and
      <link linkend="listen">socket activated by systemd</link>. In this setup
      access is controlled by a cockpit specific pam stack, generally located
      at <filename>/etc/pam.d/cockpit</filename>. By default this is configured
      to allow you to login with the username and password of any local account on the
      system. You can also setup a <link linkend="sso">Kerberos based SSO
      solution</link> or <link linkend="cert-authentication">certificate/smart
      card authentication</link>.
    </para>

    <para>You can also <ulink url="https://github.com/cockpit-project/cockpit/blob/main/doc/authentication.md#actions">disable
    authentication schemes</ulink> to enforce authentication policies, or to suppress
    undesired browser GSSAPI authentication dialogs.</para>

    <para>The web server can also be run from the
      <ulink url="https://hub.docker.com/r/cockpit/ws/">cockpit/ws</ulink>
      container. If you are running cockpit on a container host operating system like
      <ulink url="https://getfedora.org/coreos/">Fedora CoreOS</ulink>
      this will be the only supported mode. In this setup, cockpit establishes an
      SSH connection from the container to the underlying host, meaning that it is up to
      your SSH server to grant access. To login with a local account, <filename>sshd
      </filename> will need to be configured to allow password based authentication.
      Alternatively you can setup a <link linkend="sso">Kerberos based SSO
      solution</link>.</para>

    <para>Like <filename>sshd</filename>, cockpit can be configured to limit the number
      of concurrent login attempts allowed. This is done by adding a <code>MaxStartups</code>
      option to the <code>WebService</code> section of your <code>cockpit.conf</code>.
      Additional connections will be dropped until authentication succeeds or
      the connections are closed.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="direct-secondary-auth">
    <title>Directly logging into a secondary server without a primary session</title>

    <para>It is also possible to log into a secondary server without
    opening a session on the primary server. This is useful if you
    are not actually interested in the primary server and would only
    use it because you do not have direct network access to the
    secondary server.</para>

    <para>In this case, <filename>cockpit-ws</filename> still runs on
    the primary server, but the credentials from the login screen are
    directly used with SSH to log into the secondary server given in
    the "Connect To" field of the login screen.</para>

    <para>Thus, the PAM configuration and accounts on the primary
    server don't matter at all. Often, the only purpose of the primary
    server is to sit on the boundary of your network and forward
    connections to internal machines.</para>

    <para>In this case, the login page will prompt you to verify
    unknown SSH keys. Accepted keys will be remembered in the local
    storage of your browser.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="secondary-auth">
    <title>Logging into a secondary server from the primary session</title>

    <para>Once you have a session on the primary server, it is possible
    connect to additional servers by using the host switching
    UI of the Cockpit Shell. This is useful if you have direct network
    access to the primary server, but not to the secondary server.</para>

    <para>On the command line, you would log into the primary server
    and then use SSH to log into the secondary one. Cockpit does just
    the same, and uses SSH to log into the secondary server. Instead
    of running a interactive shell there, however, it starts a
    <filename>cockpit-bridge</filename> process.</para>

    <para><emphasis>Warning:</emphasis> Unlike with SSH on the command line
    though, this will also load and use the Cockpit pages (i.e. JavaScript)
    from the remote machine, which means that the remote machine can execute
    arbitrary code on your primary and all other connected secondary machines.
    Hence, only connect to <emphasis>machines which you trust</emphasis>.</para>

    <para>Due to this security risk, this host switcher functionality
    is disabled by default, except on long-term stable Linux
    distributions (Red Hat Enterprise Linux 9, Debian 12, and Ubuntu
    22.04/24.04 LTS). If you are comfortable with the security
    implications, you can enable it manually with the
    <code>AllowMultiHost</code> option in
    <filename>cockpit.conf</filename>.</para>

    <para>These servers will need to be running an SSH server
    and be configured to support one of the following
    authentication methods.</para>

    <section id="password">
      <title>Password</title>
      <para>The target server will need to have password based authentication
        enabled in <filename>sshd</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="kerberos">
      <title>Kerberos</title>
      <para>The target server will need to be a member of the same domain as the
        primary server and your domain must be whitelisted in your browser.
        See the <link linkend="sso">SSO documentation</link> for how to set
        this up.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="public-key">
      <title>Public key</title>

    <para>When you successfully log into the primary server, a
    <filename>ssh-agent</filename> is started and keys are loaded into
    it by running <filename>ssh-add</filename> without any arguments.
    Any passphrase prompt is answered with the password used to log
    into the primary server.</para>

    <para>Cockpit provides a user interface for loading other keys into the agent
      that could not be automatically loaded.</para>

    <para>The target server will need to have public key
    authentication enabled in <filename>sshd</filename>, and the
    public key you wish to use must be present in
    <filename>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>. Cockpit has a user
    interface for creating SSH keys and for authorizing them.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="host-keys">
      <title>SSH host keys</title>
      <para>Cockpit will prompt the user to verify unknown SSH host
      keys, and will write accepted host keys into
      <filename>~/.ssh/known_hosts</filename>.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
