<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id="cockpit-channels">
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>cockpit.js: Raw Channels</refname>
    <refpurpose>Raw communication channels</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>At a low level Cockpit communicates with the system via messages passed
      through various channels. These are usually exposed via higher level APIs,
      such as the <code><link linkend="cockpit-spawn">cockpit.spawn()</link></code> function.
      It is rare to use raw channels directly.</para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-channel">
    <title>cockpit.channel()</title>
<programlisting>
channel = cockpit.channel(options)
</programlisting>

    <para>This function creates a new channel for communication with the system.
      It returns a new channel object. The <code>options</code> argument is a
      plain object. At least the <code>"payload"</code> option is required, and
      based on the payload type, other options may be required.</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>"binary"</code></term>
        <listitem><para>Set to <code>true</code> to transfer binary payloads. Both messages
          sent via <link linkend="cockpit-channels-send"><code>channel.send()</code></link>
          and those received via
          <link linkend="cockpit-channels-message"><code>channel.onmessage</code></link>
          should be arrays of bytes, either <code>Uint8Array</code> or <code>Array</code>
          depending on browser support.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>"host"</code></term>
        <listitem><para>The host to open the channel to. If an alternate user or port is
          required it can be specified as <code>"user@myhost:port"</code>. If no host
          is specified then the correct one will be automatically selected based on the page
          calling this function.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>"payload"</code></term>
        <listitem><para>The payload type for the channel. Only specific payload
          types are supported.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><code>"superuser"</code></term>
        <listitem><para>Set to <code>"require"</code> to open this channel as root. If the currently
          logged in user is not permitted to become root (eg: via <code>pkexec</code>) then the
          <code>channel</code> will immediately be
          <link linkend="cockpit-channels-close-ev">closed</link> with a <code>"access-denied"</code>
          problem code.</para>
        <para>Set to <code>"try"</code> to try to open the channel as root, but if that fails,
          then fall back to an unprivileged channel.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The channel object returned has the following fields and methods and
      events. You should call the
      <code><link linkend="cockpit-channels-close">channel.close()</link></code>
      method when done with the channel.</para>

    <para>A valid channel will always be returned and the is ready to
      <code><link linkend="cockpit-channels-send">channel.send()</link></code>. The channel may
      <link linkend="cockpit-channels-close-ev">close shortly afterword</link> due
      to a failure.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-binary">
    <title>channel.binary</title>
    <para>Will be <code>true</code> for an binary channel. Will be set to <code>false</code> if the
      channel is textual.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-options">
    <title>channel.options</title>
    <para>The options used to open this channel. This should not be changed.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-valid">
    <title>channel.valid</title>
    <para>Will be <code>true</code> for an open channel. Will be set to <code>false</code> if the channel
      closes.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-send">
    <title>channel.send()</title>
<programlisting>
channel.send(data)
</programlisting>
    <para>Send a message over the channel. The contents of the message depends on the
      payload type of the channel. If a binary channel, then <code>data</code> is expected
      to be an <code>Array</code> of bytes or a <code>Uint8Array</code>. If not binary,
      then the <code>data</code> will be converted to a string if not already a string.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-control">
    <title>channel.control()</title>
<programlisting>
channel.control(options)
</programlisting>
    <para>Notify the channel to tune certain parameters on the fly. The <code>options</code>
      is a plain javascript object, and the contents depend on the <code>"payload"</code>
      of the channel.</para>
    <para>One common operation is to set <code>"command"</code> to <code>"done"</code> in the
      options field. To indicate that no further messages will be sent through the channel.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-wait">
    <title>channel.wait()</title>
<programlisting>
promise = channel.wait([callback])
</programlisting>

    <para>Returns a <code>promise</code> that is ready when the channel is ready, or fails if the
      client closes. If a <code>callback</code> is specified, it is attached to the promise. The
      promise will be rejected or resolved with the contents <code>options</code> passed to the
      <link linkend="cockpit-channels-onready">channel.onready</link> and
      <link linkend="cockpit-channels-close-ev">channel.onclose</link> events respectively.</para>
    <para>In general it's not necessary to wait for the channel before starting to use the channel.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-close">
    <title>channel.close()</title>
<programlisting>
channel.close([options])
</programlisting>
    <para>Close the channel.</para>
    <para>If <code>options</code> is present it can be a plain javascript object
      containing additional channel close options to send to the peer. If closing for
      because of a problem, set the <code>"problem"</code> field to a
      <link linkend="cockpit-problems">problem code</link>. If <code>options</code>
      is not an object it will be treated as a <code>"problem"</code>.</para>
    <para>The <link linkend="cockpit-channels-close-ev">close event</link> will fire.
      A channel can also be closed by a peer or if the underlying transport closes.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-message">
    <title>channel.onmessage</title>
<programlisting>
$(channel).on("message", function(event, data) { ... })
channel.addEventListener("message", function(event, data) { ... })
</programlisting>
    <para>An event triggered when the channel receives a message. The message is
      passed as a string to the handler in the <code>data</code>. In the case of binary
      channels <code>data</code> is an <code>Uint8Array</code> or an <code>Array</code>
      of bytes if the former is not supported by the browser. The contents of
      the message depends on the payload type of the channel.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-oncontrol">
    <title>channel.oncontrol</title>
<programlisting>
$(channel).on("control", function(event, options) { ... })
channel.addEventListener("control", function(event, options) { ... })
</programlisting>
    <para>An event triggered when the channel receives an control message in the
      middle of the flow. One particular use is when the <code>command</code> is set to
      <code>"done"</code> then no further messages will be received in the channel.
      The exact form of these messages depend on the <code>"payload"</code> of the
      channel.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-onready">
    <title>channel.onready</title>
<programlisting>
$(channel).on("ready", function(event, options) { ... })
channel.addEventListener("ready", function(event, options) { ... })
</programlisting>
    <para>An event triggered when the other end of the channel is ready to start processing
      messages. This indicates the channel is completely open. It is possible to start
      sending messages on the channel before this point.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-channels-close-ev">
    <title>channel.onclose</title>
<programlisting>
$(channel).on("close", function(options) { ... })
channel.addEventListener("close", function(event, options) { ... })
</programlisting>
    <para>An event triggered when the channel closes. This can happen either because
      <link linkend="cockpit-channels-close">channel.close()</link> function was called,
      or if the peer closed the channel, or the underlying transport closes.</para>
    <para>The <code>options</code> will contain various close information, including a
      <code>"problem"</code> field which will be set if the channel was closed because
      of a problem.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-origin">
    <title>cockpit.transport.origin</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.origin
</programlisting>
    <para>The HTTP origin that is being used by the underlying channel transport. This is
      read-only, you should not assign a value. If the browser supports
      <code>window.location.origin</code> then this will be identical to that value.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-host">
    <title>cockpit.transport.host</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.host
</programlisting>
    <para>The host that this transport is going to talk to by default. This is
      read-only, you should not assign a value. If the value is null that means that the
      transport has not been setup yet.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-csrf-token">
    <title>cockpit.transport.csrf_token</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.csrf_token
</programlisting>
    <para>A cross site request forgery token for use with external channels. This becomes
      valid once the connection is properly established.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-options">
    <title>cockpit.transport.options</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.options
</programlisting>
    <para>Initialization options received over the underlying channel transport. These
      will be empty until connection is properly established.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-wait">
    <title>cockpit.transport.wait()</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.wait(callback)
</programlisting>
    <para>Call the <code>callback</code> function once the underlying channel transport is initialized.
      This will start the initialization if not already in progress or completed. If the
      channel transport is already initialized, then <code>callback</code> will be called
      immediately.</para>
    <para>In general it's not necessary to wait for the transport before starting to open channels.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-close">
    <title>cockpit.transport.close()</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.close([problem])
</programlisting>
    <para>Close the underlying channel transport. All channels open channels will close.
      The <code>problem</code> argument should be a problem code string. If not specified
      it will default to <code>"disconnected"</code>.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-filter">
    <title>cockpit.transport.filter()</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.filter(function(message, channelid, control) { ... }, [out])
</programlisting>
    <para>Add a filter to the underlying channel transport. All incoming messages will be
      passed to each of the filter callbacks that are registered. If the <code>out</code>
      argument is equal to <code>true</code> then the filter will receive outgoing messages
      that being sent on the underlying channel transport.</para>
    <para>This function is rarely used.</para>
    <para>Filter callbacks are called in the order they are registered. If a filter
      callback returns <code>false</code> then the message will not be dispatched
      further, whether to other filters, or to channels, etc.</para>

    <para>The <code>message</code> is the string or array with the raw message including,
      the framing. The <code>channelid</code> is the channel identifier or an empty string
      for control messages. If <code>control</code> is set then this is a control message,d
      and the <code>control</code> argument contains the parsed JSON object of the
      control message.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-transport-inject">
    <title>cockpit.transport.inject()</title>
<programlisting>
cockpit.transport.inject(message, [out])
</programlisting>
    <para>Inject a message into the underlying channel transport. The <code>message</code>
      should be a <code>string</code> or an array of bytes, and should be valid
      according to the Cockpit message protocol. If the <code>out</code> argument is equal
      to <code>false</code> then the message will be injected as an incoming message as if
      it was received on the underlying channel transport.</para>
    <para>This function is rarely used. In general you should only <code>inject()</code>
      messages you got from a <code><link linkend="cockpit-transport-filter">filter()</link></code>.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-base64-encode">
    <title>cockpit.base64_encode()</title>
<programlisting>
string = cockpit.base64_encode(data)
</programlisting>
    <para>Encode binary data into a string using the Base64 encoding. The <code>data</code>
      argument can either be a <code>string</code>, an <code>Array</code>, an <code>ArrayBuffer</code>
      or a <code>Uint8Array</code>. The return value is a string.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-base64-decode">
    <title>cockpit.base64_decode()</title>
<programlisting>
data = cockpit.base64_decode(string, [constructor])
</programlisting>
    <para>Decode binary data from a Base64 encoded string. The <code>string</code>
      argument should be a javascript string. The returned <code>data</code>> will be an
      array of bytes.</para>
    <para>You can pass <code>Uint8Array</code>, <code>Array</code> or <code>String</code>
      as an alternate <code>constructor</code> if you want the decoded data in an
      alternate form. The default is to return an <code>Array</code>. Note that if you use a
      <code>String</code> for the decoded data, then you must guarantee that the data
      does not contain bytes that would be invalid for a string.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-utf8-encoder">
    <title>cockpit.utf8_encoder()</title>
<programlisting>
encoder = cockpit.utf8_encoder([constructor])
</programlisting>
    <para>Create an encoder for encoding a string into a UTF8 sequence of bytes.</para>
    <para>You can pass <code>Uint8Array</code>, <code>Array</code> or <code>String</code>
      as an alternate <code>constructor</code> if you want the decoded data in an
      alternate form. The default is to return an <code>Array</code>.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-utf8-encoder-encode">
    <title>encoder.encode()</title>
<programlisting>
data = encoder.encode(string)
</programlisting>
    <para>Encode a <code>string</code> into a UTF8 sequence of bytes.</para>
    <para>The resulting <code>data</code> is an array of bytes, but it's type may be
      modified by passing an alternate <code>constructor</code> to
      <link linkend="cockpit-utf8-encoder">cockpit.utf8_encoder()</link>.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-utf8-decoder">
    <title>cockpit.utf8_decoder()</title>
<programlisting>
decoder = cockpit.utf8_decoder([fatal])
</programlisting>
    <para>Creates a decoder to decode a UTF8 sequence of bytes data into a string.</para>
    <para>If the <code>fatal</code> is set to <code>true</code> then the <code>decoder</code>
      will throw an exception when it encounters invalid UTF8 data. By default invalid data
      will be substituted with special UTF8 characters.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsection id="cockpit-utf8-decoder-decode">
    <title>decoder.decode()</title>
<programlisting>
string = decoder.decode(data, [options])
</programlisting>
    <para>Decode an array of UTF8 bytes into a <code>string</code>. The <code>data</code>
      argument may be an <code>Array</code>, a <code>Uint8Array</code> or a string containing
      binary data.</para>
    <para>If <code>options</code> is passed it should be a plain javascript object. If
      <code>options</code> has a <code>stream</code> property equal to <code>true</code>,
      then multiple invocations of this function can be made with parts of the UTF8 sequence
      of bytes. Any trailing bytes that don't yet build a complete unicode character, will be
      cached until the next invocation. To drain the last data, call this function without
      the <code>stream</code> property set.</para>
  </refsection>

</refentry>
