<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="https">
  <title>SSL/TLS Usage</title>

  <para>Cockpit usually requires that web browsers communicate with it using HTTPS,
    for security reasons.</para>

  <section id="https-required">
    <title>HTTPS Requirement</title>

    <para>Cockpit listens for both HTTP and HTTPS connections on the same port, by
      default 9090. If an HTTP connection is made, Cockpit will redirect that
      connection to HTTPS. There are some exceptions:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If an HTTP connection comes from <code>localhost</code> (<code>127.0.0.1</code> or
        <code>::1</code>, then Cockpit will allow communication without redirecting to HTTPS.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Certain URLs, like <code>/ping</code> are not required to use
        HTTPS.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This behavior can be overridden by setting the
      <code>AllowUnencrypted</code> option in <code>cockpit.conf</code>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="https-certificates">
    <title>Certificates</title>

    <para>Cockpit will load a certificate from the <code>/etc/cockpit/ws-certs.d</code>,
    directory, or below <code>$XDG_CONFIG_DIRS</code> if set (see
      <ulink url="./cockpit.conf.5.html">cockpit.conf</ulink>).
      It will use the last file with a <code>.cert</code> or <code>.crt</code>
      extension in alphabetical order. The file should contain one or more OpenSSL
      style <literal>BEGIN CERTIFICATE</literal> blocks for the server certificate and
      the intermediate certificate authorities.</para>

    <para>
      The private key must be contained in a separate file with the same name as the
      certificate, but with a <code>.key</code> suffix instead. The key must not be
      encrypted.</para>

    <para>If no certificate is found, a self-signed certificate is created and
      stored in the <filename>0-self-signed.cert</filename> file. On some
      platforms, Cockpit will also generate a ca.crt in that directory, which
      may be safely imported into client browsers.</para>

    <para>Cockpit will read the files as root, so they can have tight
      permissions.</para>

    <para>To check which certificate <code>cockpit-ws</code> will use run
      the following command.</para>
<programlisting>
$ sudo /usr/libexec/cockpit-certificate-ensure --check
</programlisting>
    <para>Or, on Debian-based systems:</para>
<programlisting>
$ sudo /usr/lib/cockpit/cockpit-certificate-ensure --check
</programlisting>

    <para>If using <code>certmonger</code> to manage certificates, following command can
    be used to automatically prepare a certificate/key file pair:</para>

    <programlisting>
getcert request -f /etc/cockpit/ws-certs.d/50-certmonger.cert \
                -k /etc/cockpit/ws-certs.d/50-certmonger.key \
                -D myhostname.example.com \
                [--ca=...]</programlisting>

    <para>This will not work on Red Hat Enterprise Linux 8 by default. Adjust the SELinux type of the certificate directory to <code>cert_t</code> to allow certmonger to write its certificates there:</para>

    <programlisting>
semanage fcontext -a -t cert_t '/etc/cockpit/ws-certs\.d(/.*)?'
restorecon -v /etc/cockpit/ws-certs.d</programlisting>
  </section>

</chapter>
