<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="modules">
  <title>Cockpit Modules</title>

  <para>Cockpit is separated into various modules, each of which brings specific
    features and/or code.</para>

  <warning>
    <para>It is not yet possible to implement arbitrary new modules.</para>

    <para>In addition, any APIs or behavior not explicitly documented here is an
      internal API and can be changed at any time.</para>
  </warning>

  <section id="module-layout">
    <title>Layout of Module Files</title>

    <para>A module consists of one or more files placed in a directory or its
      subdirectories. It must have a <code>manifest.json</code> file and follow
      certain naming conventions.</para>

    <para>The name of a module is the name of the directory.</para>

    <para>The name of the module and all file and directory names must be ASCII
      alphanumeric and may only contain a dash, underscore, dot and comma.  No spaces are
      allowed.</para>

    <para>Cockpit uses the data directories from the
      <ulink url="http://standards.freedesktop.org/basedir-spec/basedir-spec-latest.html">XDG Base Directory
        Specification</ulink>
      to locate modules. The <code>$XDG_DATA_DIRS</code> represents a colon separate list of system data
      directories, and <code>$XDG_DATA_HOME</code> is a user specific data directory. If the environment
      variables are not set, defaults are used, according to the spec.</para>

    <para>A <code>cockpit/</code> subdirectories in any of these data directories is the location where
      modules are loaded by Cockpit. If Cockpit finds a module with the same name, in multiple data
      directories, then the first one wins. According to the spec the first data directory is
      <code>$XDG_DATA_HOME</code> and then <code>$XDG_DATA_DIRS</code> in order.</para>

    <para>This means that, by default the following directories are searched for cockpit modules, and
      in this order:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><code>~/.local/share/cockpit/</code></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>/usr/local/share/cockpit/</code></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><code>/usr/share/cockpit/</code></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Modules placed in <code>$XDG_DATA_HOME</code> are not cached by Cockpit or the web browser.
      Other modules are cached agressively, and are accessed using a checksum of the files in
      the module and their names.</para>

    <para>To further clarify things, here is an example module called "my-module" and its file layout:</para>

<programlisting>
/usr/share/cockpit/
    my-module/
        manifest.json
        file.html
        some.js
</programlisting>

    <para>Place or symlink modules in your <code>~/.local/share/cockpit</code> directory (or appropriate
      <code>$XDG_DATA_HOME</code> location) that you would like to modify and develop. System installed
      modules should not change while Cockpit is running.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="module-manifest">
    <title>Module Manifest</title>

    <para>Each module has a <code>manifest.json</code> file. It is a JSON object. The following
      fields may be present in the manifest:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>version</term>
        <listitem><para>An informational version number for the module.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

</chapter>
