<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="multi-host">
  <title>
    Managing multiple hosts at the same time
  </title>

  <para>
    Cockpit allows you to access multiple hosts in a single session,
    by establishing SSH connections to other hosts. This is quite
    similar to logging into these other hosts using the "ssh" command
    on the command line, with one very important difference:
  </para>
  <para>
    Code from the local host and all the remote hosts run at the same
    time, in the same browser context.  They are not sufficiently
    isolated from each other in the browser. All code effectively has
    the same privileges as the primary session on the local host.
  </para>
  <para>
    Thus, <emphasis>you should only only connect to remote hosts that
    you trust</emphasis>. You must be sure that none of the hosts that
    you connect to will cause Cockpit to load malicious JavaScript
    code into your browser.
  </para>
  <para>
    Going forward, Cockpit will try to provide sufficient isolation to
    make it safe to manage multiple hosts in a single Cockpit
    session. But until we get there, Cockpit will at least warn you
    before connecting to more than one host. It is also possible to
    disable multiple hosts entirely, and some operating systems do
    this already by default.
  </para>
  <para>
    You can prevent loading of JavaScript, HTML, etc from more than
    one host by adding this to <filename>cockpit.conf</filename>:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
    [WebService]
    AllowMultiHost=false
  </programlisting>
  <para>
    When you allow multiple hosts in a single Cockpit session by
    setting <code>AllowMultiHost</code> to true, then the user will be
    warned once per session, before connecting to the second host.  If
    that is still too much, you can switch it off completely by adding
    the following to <filename>cockpit.conf</filename>:
  </para>
  <programlisting>
    [Session]
    WarnBeforeConnecting=false
  </programlisting>
</chapter>
